A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Media Policy collection FA722
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Media Policy collection
1964-1980
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA722
0.94 Cubic Feet 2 legal document boxes
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Scope and Contents
The Ford Foundation records, Media Policy Collection consists of reports, correspondence, and court briefs from 1968-1992. The materials originate from the Ford Foundation Grant #06800203 awarded to the United Church of Christ to combat racial discrimination in broadcasting and broadcast employment.
Arrangement
The Media Policy Collection consists of a single series: United Church of Christ.
Biographical / Historical
Reverend Everett Carleton Parker established the United Church of Christ Office of Communications in 1954 as a way to change the racial disparity and presentation of social justics issues for black Americans on the nation's local television screens. Through Parker's work, the church was named as a petitioner in the TV license renewal hearing for WLBT in Jackson, Mississippi. In 1969, WLBT was the first TV station to lose its right to broadcast for adhering to pro-segregationist programming. The Ford Foundation made the first two-year grant (Grant #06800203) to the United Church of Christ Office of Communication to "redress racial imbalance in service and programming in broadcasting in 12 southern cities" on January 31, 1968. The Foundation provided $990,000 to the UCC over the next ten years. The Foundation has provided subsequent grants to the church to support conferences and leadership summits in the 1990s and 2000s.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary. The materials were accessioned at Ford as Accession 2004/015 on July 6, 2004. Additional materials may be added to this collection in the future.
Ford Foundation; Television broadcasting--United States; Civil rights -- History
- United Church of Christ, 1964-1991; I; 0.94 Cubic Feet 2 legal document boxes
  Arrangement
  Series I, United Church of Christ, is arranged in the following subseries:
  A. Broadcast Monitoring Study, 1964-1966 B. Letters, 1979-1980 C. Lamar Life Broadcasting D. Check Your Local Stations E. Court Briefs F. Reports and statements G. Handbooks
  - Broadcast Monitoring Study, 1964-1966; A
    - "Observation of Television Programming." Packet of instructions and an Observer's Log Sheet issued by the Office of Communication, United Church of Christ (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Attachment A. "Relevant facts concerning churches and instrumentalities of the United Church of Christ." Includes exhibits 1 and 2 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Attachment B. "Documents relative to the monitoring study." Exhibit #1a-d and Exhibit #2 are listed, however, Exhibit #1d and Exhibit #2 are missing, 1964 March 1 - 7 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Budget – "Television Monitoring Study and Legal Briefs, Jackson, Mississippi, April, 1964 through May, 1966", 1964 April - 1966 May (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters, 1979-1980; B
    - Letter from George A. Owens, President and Robert O. Wilder, Chairman of Tougaloo College to Dr. C. Shelby Rooks, Chairman, Seminary Section of the CHE, Chicago Theological Seminary, 1980 September 12 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Two letters of support sent to Reverend Everett C. Parker, Director, Office of Communications, United Church of Christ, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Lamar Life Broadcasting, 1964-1969; C
    Scope and Contents
    Folder 5 contains documents related to case number 19409 in the United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit. Office of Communications of the United Church of Christ, Aaron Henry Robert L.T. Smith, and United Church of Christ at Tougaloo, Appellants, v. Federal Communications Commission, Appellee, Lamar Life Broadcasting Company, Intervenor.
    - "Analysis of Programming of WLBT, Channel 3 for period March 1 through March 7 inclusive by program type" (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Attachment J. "Use of Mr., Mrs., and Miss in the News." A statement by Dick Sanders, New Director of Station WLBT. Or the reverse side is Attachment K – List of local Negro Programs Scheduled on WLBT-TV since March 1, 1964: (Excluding Announcements, Local News and Local Sports), 1964 May 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Petition to intervene and to deny application for renewal of operation license (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Opposition to the petition (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Reply to the opposition. All three documents were submitted to the Federal Communications Commission (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Dockets from hearing before the Federal Communications Commission regarding application of the Lamar Life Insurance Company for renewal of license of television station WLBT and auxiliary services, Jackson Mississippi, 1967-1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Brief for Intervenor, 1969 January 10 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Reply Brief for Appellants, 1965 November 3 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Brief for Appellants (photocopy) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Broadcast Bureau's Comments on Petition for Reconsideration" (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Opposition to Motion to Designate Place of Hearing" (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Reply of Appellants on Motion to clarify this Court's Opinion and Order" (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Statement of Commissioner Kenneth A. Cox Concurring in Part and Dissenting in Part" (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Memorandum Opinion and Order" (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Notice of Appeal" (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Check Your Local Stations, 1976-1979; D
    Check Your Local Stations was a program created by the Office of Communications of the United Church of Christ to teach community leaders about communication law and ways to improve broadcasting services to minorities.
    - Memo regarding Check Your Local Stations regional workshops to train community leaders to "negotiate with broadcasters for improved radio and television service and employment practices" (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Citizen Action in Telecommunications Workshop. Handbook for Participants by Robert Lewis Shayon. A joint program of Office of Communication, United Church of Christ and Media Reform Committee, National Organization for Women, 1979 March 30-31 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Report to the Veatch Program, 1976 January 30-1977 April 30 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Report to the Veatch Program, 1978 January 1-December 15 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Court Briefs, 1968; E
    - Court Brief in the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Seventh Circuit, Nos. 16,369, 16498, and 16,499. Columbia Broadcasting System, Inc., National Broadcasting Company, Inc., and Radio Television News Directors Associations et al., Petitioners v. Unites States of America, and Federal Communications Commission, Respondents. On petition for Review of an Order of the Federal Communications Commission. (photocopy) (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Court Brief No. 2 and 717 in the Supreme Court of the United States. October Term, 1968. United States of America and Federal Communications Commission, Petitioners v. Radio Television news directors Association, et al., Respondents. Red Lion Broadcasting Co., Inc., et al., Petitioners, v. Federal Communications Commission, Respondent. (photocopy), 1968 October (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Reports and statements, 1969-1991; F
    - Grant No. 68-203. Report to the Ford Foundation. Exhibit #1 – Petition to Deny Renewal of License of KTAL-TV, 1969 March 7 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Grant No. 680-0203D. Report to the Ford Foundation. Office of Communications. United Church of Christ, 1973 October (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Report to Field Foundation AFL-CIO. Office of Communication. United Church of Christ, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - "Excerpts from a statement by a joint committee of the World Association for Christian Communication and the National Council of the Churches of Christ in the U.S.A. on 'Communication in an Emerging World Order'" (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - "Broadcast Television in a Multichannel Marketplace" by Florence Setzer and Jonathan Levy. OPP Working Paper No. 26. Office of Plans and Policy. Federal Communications Commission, 1991 June (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Handbooks, 1979; G
    - "Public Action for Radio Workshop." Handbook for Participants by Robert Lewis Shayon. A Project of Telecommunications Consumer Coalition, 1979 December 15 (Box 2, Folder 14)